[Music]
hello and welcome to this video at the
end of this video we'll be able to
interact with our npcs and utilize the
shop system ui that we made in the last
video so we're going to come over here
we can press e to interact with our npcs
so we'll press e and it'll bring up the
shop window it's going to list all of
the items that the shop has in stock so
you can see from our scripts of objects
that there's 99 cogs 10 health potions
and one sword item in this shop
and the shop has a thousand gold
available so let's just jump straight
into this video okay so let's just
continue where we left off so in the
previous episode we'd set up the canvas
and we'd made this shopkeeper display
script but it currently doesn't do
anything so let's make it do some stuff
okay so the first thing that it would
make sense to do is actually to spawn
the um the items from the shop in our
shop list on that left-hand panel so
let's set that up first so we'll do a
public void display
shop
window and in here this will take in a
shop system we'll just call this oh
let's call that shop system and we'll do
player inventory holder and we'll call
this player inventory holder so let's
assign the um
shop system and the player inventory
holder to some sort of like uh
script-wide variables that we can kind
of keep a reference to so we'll do a
private shop system and we'll call this
underscore shop system and we'll do a
private player inventory holder and
we'll call that player imagery holder so
the first thing we'll do is we'll get
our shop system and we'll get underscore
shop system and we'll equal this to shop
system and underscore player inventory
holder and we'll equal this to player
inventory holder and then we'll refresh
the display which is going to be a new
method that we'll make so we'll do
private
void refresh display and the first thing
we'll do here is we'll clear our slots
you'll notice this is seeming and this
is sounding a little bit like the uh
dynamic inventory display and our um
static inventory display there's not
really a huge amount of copied
functionality like we don't need to
click on the slots or anything um so i
didn't want to kind of have shopkeeper
display derive from inventory display
but of course there are um some
functions that are of course there are
some stuff kind of in common so for
example uh clear slots but we're not
going to copy this over wholesale i just
thought i'd point that out and i am
aware that there's similar sort of
naming but they're not that they're
different enough to not kind of need to
derive from uh inventory display so i'm
gonna have uh clear slots and this is
gonna be a private void clear slots so
this is going to loop through every uh
item in our um item
content
list panel and
a dot transform and then we'll do cast
transform so that's just like we're
doing here but we're doing it on our
display i'm going to destroy item dot
gameobject then we're going to do the
exact same thing again on the shopping
cart content panel that's going to clear
the slots and we actually need two
dictionaries which are going to keep
track of um what we have in our shopping
cart so let's come up here and we'll do
um private private dictionary which is
going to take in inventory item data as
well as an int and this is going to be
our shopping cart which is going to be a
new dictionary
of inventory item data's an int and then
we're going to have a private dictionary
again of inventory item data and this is
going to be the ui kind of side of it
and this is going to take in our
shopping cart item ui and this will be
the shopping cart and this will be the
shopping cart uh i'll call it ui so this
equal to a new dictionary but there's
our two dictionaries so as well as in
in clear slots as well as deleting all
of these items we're going to clear out
these um lists uh these dictionaries as
well we're just going to delete them
make new ones that replace them with
these new um dictionaries to make sure
they're nice and fresh and so that's our
clear slots function which we need in
our refresh display and then we're gonna
disable the basket total text because
obviously there won't be anything in the
basket at first
we may as well disable it you could also
just set it to zero
um but i am going to set it uh to false
so basket total text dot enabled is
equal to false gonna turn off the buy
button so buy button dot game object
active false and we're going to make
another int up here uh we'll do it here
so private and this is the basket total
this is going to keep track of how much
our basket is going to
um so obviously when we're refreshing
the display and the slots have been
cleared we can actually set that back to
zero because that we know there's
nothing in the basket so it won't be
worth any kind of amount of gold and we
can refresh the text we can do player
gold dot text is equal to
um ring so player gold we'll set this
equal to the player inventory holder dot
inventory system dot
gold and i don't think we've actually
implemented that yet so let's go over to
the primary inventory system that's
actually um serialized field private and
gold so let's introduce the concept of
gold to our inventory system and we'll
do public int gold and we'll return gold
our private in gold up here and then as
well as this public inventory system
constructor we're going to make another
one which can now give us some gold so
public inventory system which will take
in a size and a gold amount and here we
can say
gold is equal to gold and then we will
call our um here we say gold is equal to
the gold amount that we've passed in and
here we'll just set gold to
zero as a default and i'm going to take
this bit of code and i'm gonna a private
void
method called create inventory which
takes in a size and then we can just say
create inventory size and
down here as well so we've got two
constructors now one just takes in a
size one takes in some gold to give to
the player so we've introduced the
concept of gold to our inventory system
let's go back over to shopkeeper display
so we've now got gold so we're going to
display the player gold and then we want
to do the same but for the shop hold
text and then we'll say shop gold and
this will take from the shop system the
available gold and i don't think that's
um we haven't got a kind of getter for
that so we'll just do public and
available gold which will return
available gold and then we'll go back
over to our shopkeeper display and you
can see that that's working there now
okay so now we just want to
make another method and this one is
going to be a private void display shot
inventory and i'm we're not going to use
this one just yet but i'm just going to
make a private void display player
inventory as well just while we're doing
that and so up in refresh display let's
call that so display um shop inventory
and all we're going to do in this method
is we're going to loop through every
item in our shop systems inventory so
shop system dot
items which i don't think we can get
it's this shop inventory here we need to
allow a getter for that so public list
of shop slots
all shop inventory which will allow us
to get the shop inventory
um variable go back over here and we can
say for every item in our shops
inventory if the item dot item data is
equal to null then let's just continue
because we only want to populate we only
want to spawn in a slot if it's not null
and then we say bar
slot is equal to instantiate the shop
slot prefab underneath our shop list
panel what's it called underneath our
item list content panel dot transform
then we can initialize the shop slot so
shop slot init and this is gonna pass in
our item along with the shop system dot
buy markup which again we can't get i'm
gonna do a public
float uh buy mark up which will return
the buy markup and then we might as well
do the cell markup while we're here we
will need to do that so this init
function this is going to be on our shop
slot ui um class that we made and never
did anything with so let's do a public
void in it which will take in shop slot
and a float oh shop
slot slot and float uh markup okay so
let's work now on initializing our shop
slot so we'll go over to the shop slot
ui class and we'll serialize field
private image in unity engine ui uh
item sprite we'll do
serialized field private
text mesh pro u guy item name and let's
just uh duplicate that to be item and
we'll do a serialized field private shop
slot signed item slot so in our awake
function we're going to
set the item sprite dot sprite equal to
null uh item
sprite dot preserve aspect equal to true
item sprite dot color equal to color dot
clear item name dot text is
equal to match the blank string and item
count dot text again equal to a blind
string an empty string we want our
buttons as well so we want a
um serialize field private button and
this is the add to cart button so add
item to cart as well as a remove
item from cart button i'll call these
buttons just so we know exactly what
they are so to our buttons we're going
to add some methods so we're going to
say add item to cart button if it's not
null we're going to uh
we're going to add a listener to the on
click button and it's going to be an add
item to cart method we've got remove
item from cart on click we'll add
listener we'll remove item rom cart and
we can also get a private shopkeeper
display let's call this parent display
once you're gonna make this public with
a getter and private setter we don't
need to assign that in the inspector so
we're just going to get private set
parent display is equal to transform dot
parent dot get component in parent dot
display now let's make these functions
here so add item to cart let's create a
method for that and let's create a
method for remove item from cart okay so
all we start hooking up these buttons
and making them work let's get rid of
these throw new not implemented
exceptions i'm gonna make a private void
um update ui slot which is gonna take in
chop slot of shop slot as well as the
markup so float price
markup and i'm going to move this init
function up here just so it follows a
bit more of a logical order so in our
init function i'm just going to set our
assigned item slot equal to slot and
call update ui slot passing in our shop
slot and
markup and then in our update ui slot we
can say if assigned item slot dot data
is not equal to null just as a check
we're going to say item sprite dot
sprite is equal to signed item slot or
item data dot icon we can set the item
sprite dot color equal to color dot
white the item count doxed be equal to
the item slot assigned item slot dot
stack size dot who string and then the
item name dot text is going to be equal
to item slot signed item slot dot data
dot display name and then for now we're
just going to do um the item slot item
data dot value so this isn't going to
take into account the markup for now but
let's just um let's just get this in and
work in and then here we can say uh else
so if the item is null and let's just uh
clear the slot out so that's that there
and think about it we don't actually
need to pass in shop slot like that
let's just get rid of those um and then
let's store this markup so we can use it
later in a public float
markup again with a get and private set
and here we'll just say markup is equal
to markup just so we can access that
down here when we do actually want to
use the markup and then assigned item
slot obviously we're setting here when
we initialize it and then just to make
sure the buttons are getting um set up
properly and kind of registered to these
events let's just say let's debug.log
adding item to cart and then
removing item rom cart okay so now on
our ui controller here when we set our
um display to active so when we interact
with the npcs and we turn on the shop
window we want to set it active and then
we want to call the display shop window
method on this function and we can pass
in the shop system and the player
inventory here so we're going to
interact with npc it's going to call
this method which is going to turn on
the actual game object so it pops up and
we can see it and then we're going to
call the display shop menu a shop window
method
that's going to set up the shop system
in the player inventory holder and then
it's going to refresh the display which
is going to clear any slots that were
already there on the panel it will then
reset all of the sort of text and the
variables and then it will display the
shop inventory which is going to spawn
in our shop system prefab it's going to
instantiate them under the
scroll list that we set up on the left
hand side then it should initialize the
shop slot with the item so let's see if
that actually works so let's hit play
and before we do that we need to set up
some stuff obviously
i always forget to do that let's go to
our prefabs we've got our shopping list
item ui and you can see that we've now
got all of these um fields that we need
to fill in so drag in the item sprite
item name item count we don't need to do
anything with the assigned item slot but
we can drag in the add item to cart
button as well as the remove from cart
button okay so hopefully we've not
missed something we probably have let's
hit play and just see what happens and
see in which way it breaks let's go over
here so this is one of our npcs we can
open it oh and there you go i'm
surprised that worked first time so
we've got our cogs which are worth 1g
our health potions which cost 100 g had
our sword items which he's got one of
they cost 100 g as well um currently
i've got no way to close the panel uh
which is a bit of a an oversight so
let's uh come out and go back in here
this has got our sword they've got 10 of
them at the sword shop and then we can
come over here we can access the potion
shop and we've got the poison potion and
health potion and okay i know this was a
bit of a shorter video but i'm gonna
leave this one here because in the next
video we're gonna set up the actual
shopping cart system and there's a lot
of quite like dense kind of stuff we
need to do
involving kind of like the marking up of
the items um so i'd rather do that in
its own separate video to try and keep
that one concise but hopefully you liked
this video
uh all of the kind of series doing this
shop system is already available over on
patreon.com along with the project files
so if you don't want to wait a week for
the next part feel free to head over to
the patreon and if you support me there
you'll get access to the videos kind of
early because they're all done filmed
i'd just like to take a minute to thank
all of my patrons on screen now we can
see the 10 000 xp tier which is a sector
sweep and i want to thank all of the 4
000 xp tier members as well if you need
any help with this video or any of the
other videos in this series leave a
comment below or head over to the
discord server where you should be able
to get an answer from me there and in
the meantime thanks for watching and
i'll see you in the next one bye
you